<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<language>en</language>
<item>
<title>Holocene  shore  displacement  in  the  surroundings  of  Tallinn, North  Estonia</title>
<author>Saarse, L., Vassiljev, J.</author>
<description>Abstract. The Tallinn area was recovered from the Weichselian ice sheet not later than 13 000 - 12 800 cal yr BP but remained for 
ca 1500 years under the waters of the Baltic Ice Lake (BIL). The highest parts of Tallinn emerged from the BIL after its drainage 
about 11 600 cal yr BP. At the beginning of the Yoldia Sea stage the present city area was submerged by sea water, except for the 
highest parts of Viimsi, Lasnamäe and Nõmme. At the end of the Yoldia Sea stage the Ülemiste, Pääsküla and Männiku basins 
isolated from the sea. During the Ancylus Lake transgression about 10 300 cal yr BP the highest coastline at 34 - 36 m a.s.l. 
broadly outlined the klint escarpment. The Litorina Sea transgressional coastline at 7800 - 7600 cal yr BP and beach formations at 
21 - 22 m a.s.l. are less developed than the Ancylus ones and often covered by aeolian deposits. Toompea arched north as a cape in 
the Litorina Sea and the previous Viimsi Island joined with the mainland. During the Limnea Sea stage (4400 cal yr BP up to the 
present, the highest coastline at ca 12 m a.s.l.) land increased mostly at the back of Kakumäe and Kopli bays. The Kakumäe 
Peninsula obtained its outline about 2800 years ago, the Kopli Peninsula ca 1000 years later. The Paljassaar Peninsula was the 
latest to be formed ca 100 years ago. The attached palaeogeographical maps display shore displacement during the different stages 
of the Baltic Sea in the vicinity of Tallinn.</description>
<guid>Estonian Journal of Earth Sciences, 2010, 59, 3, 207 - 215; doi: 10.3176/earth.2010.3.03</guid>
<link>http://www.kirj.ee/public/Estonian_Journal_of_Earth_Sciences/2010/issue_3/earth-2010-3-207-215.pdf</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<legends>Baltic_Sea.jpg</legends>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
